A Guide to the Katie J. Owen Papers, 1842-1983 (bulk 1875-1945)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Katie J. Owen Papers, 1842-1983 (bulk 1875-1945)
The Library of Virginia
43474
4.5 cubic feet (12 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Judy Jordan Owen, Harpers Ferry, West Virginia.
Biographical Information
Katherine (Katie) Byrd Jordan was born in Front Royal, Warren County, Virginia on 18 October 1894. She was the daughter of William Absalom Jordan, Sr. (1862-1904) and Martha Catherine Hudnall (1865-1940). She graduated from Front Royal High School in 1912, and attended the State Teachers College in Harrisonburg from 1914-1915. Afterwards, she taught at schools in Berryville, Ivor, and Wylliesburg. On 5 February 1919, she married Otis Oscar Owen (b. 1897) in Washington, D.C. Following their marriage, they lived in Charlotte County, Virginia for a short time. He then moved to Roanoke where he resided. They had one son, Otis Oscar ("Dick") Owen, Jr. (1920-1997). They were divorced in 1942. She then resided in Washington, D.C., and was employed in various retail establishments. She later moved back to Front Royal, and was active in the Warren Rifles Chapter of the United Daughters of the Confederacy. Katie J. Owen died in Front Royal on 2 January 1988, and is buried in Prospect Hill Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1842-1983, of Katie J. Owen (1894-1988) of Front Royal, Virginia, including correspondence, subject files, account books and ledgers, and ephemera. The bulk of the collection covers the years 1875-1945.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Correspondence.
II. Subject Files.
III. Account Books and Ledgers.
IV. Ephemera.
V. Oversize.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1850-1983., Extent: 1 box. (Box 1)
  The correspondence dates from 1850 to 1983, and the earliest letters are between members of the Newman family, including Isaac Van Meter Newman (b. 1835) and William W. Newman (1825-1884), and their sister Mary Katherine (Newman) Jordan (1822-1909). Topics include land sales, farming, weather, and health. The later correspondence is written to Mary Katherine Jordan and her husband Absalom Jordan (1813-1879). Many of the letters were written by his sister Susie Emma (Jordan) Millan (1865-1938) regarding her financial affairs. There are also numerous letters from Mary Katherine Jordan to her daughters Katie and Virginia Jordan while they were living with their aunt Mary Elizabeth (Jordan) Ferguson (1860-1919). Most of the post-1920 correspondence is addressed to Katie J. Owen, and much of it is from attorneys and insurance agents. There are also letters written by her husband Otis O. Owen, Sr. (b. 1897) while he was living and working in Roanoke.
  Chronological.
  - 1850-1889. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1890-1899. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1900-1909. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1910-1919. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1920-1924. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1925. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1926. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1927-1929. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1930-1932. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1933-1939. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1940-1945. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1946-1949. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1963-1983. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series II. Subject Files., Extent: 9 boxes. (Box 2-10)
  The subject files include accounts and receipts, address books, agreements and contracts, certificates, clippings, and Confederate States historical information. There is also correspondence Owen received from Francisco Colon Gordiany, who was a member of the Puerto Rico House of Representatives. The letters date from 1930 to 1932, and many of them discuss politics on the island. There are also papers of Mary E. Ferguson, including accounts and receipts, bank books, correspondence, insurance papers, and tax records. Also included in the subject files are deeds, genealogical notes on the Eastham, Jordan, and Newman families, greeting cards, guardian's accounts, insurance policies, invitations, "love letters" from Otis Owen to Katie Owen, poetry, programs, and postcards. There are two large photo albums of Lucy Josephine (Hudnall) Salisbury (1855-1915), as well as numerous other family photographs, many of which are identified. There are also tax tickets and receipts, copies of the wills of Mary E. Ferguson and Katie J. Owen, and other items.
  Alphabetical.
  - Accounts and Receipts, 1856-1899. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Accounts and Receipts, 1900-1909. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Accounts and Receipts, 1910-1919. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Accounts and Receipts, 1920-1921. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Accounts and Receipts, 1922-1929. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Accounts and Receipts, 1930-1939. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Accounts and Receipts, 1940-1949. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Accounts and Receipts, 1950-1979. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Accounts and Receipts, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Address Books. (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
  - Addresses. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Admission Tickets. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Agreements and Contracts. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Almanac (portion). (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Applications. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Baby Book - Otis Oscar Owen, Jr.. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Baseball Schedules. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "Belle Boyd - Southern Spy of the Shenandoah". (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Boy Scouts. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Broadside. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Brook Hill Estates. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Calendars. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Calling/Business Cards. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Certificates. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Clippings. (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Colon Gordiany, Francisco. (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - "Confederate History of Alexandria" by William Robert Adam, UDC Essay. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Confederate Soldier Fathers of Members," Warren Rifles Chapter, Front Royal, Virginia Division No. 95, General Organization No. 934, United Daughters of the Confederacy. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Deeds. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Diaries, 1930-1931. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Divorce. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Election Ticket, 1912. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Envelopes. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Equal Suffrage League Fliers. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Ferguson, Mary E. - Accounts and Receipts. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Ferguson, Mary E. - Agreements. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Ferguson, Mary E. - Bank Books. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Ferguson, Mary E. - Correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Ferguson, Mary E. - Deed, 1910. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Ferguson, Mary E. - Insurance. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Ferguson, Mary E. - Tax Tickets and Receipts. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Front Royal Methodist Church. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Front Royal/Warren County Historical Facts. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Genealogical Notes. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Greeting Cards. (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Guardian's Accounts. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "A History of the Graduating Class of 1912". (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Hudnall, Annie E.. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Insurance Policies. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Inventory of Absalom Jordan's Property, 1868. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Inventory and Appraisment - Martha C. Jordan Home, 1910. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Invitations. (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
  - "Jefferson Davis' Service to the United States". (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Memorandum Book. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Memorial Record - Martha Catherine Jordan, 1940. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "Memories in Marble: The Story of Front Royal's Four Confederate Monuments". (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Newman - Family and War Records. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Notebook - Confederate States History. (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
  - Owen, Otis O. - "Love Letters". (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
  - Pay Stubs - Otis O. Owen, Jr., 1944. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Photograph Albums (2) of Lucy Josephine Salisbury. (Box 8)
  - Photographs. (Box 9)
  - Poetry. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Postcard Album. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Postcard Album (Empty). (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Postcards. (Box 10)
  - Prescriptions. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Program - Field Day, Randolph-Macon Academy, 1912. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Program - Front Royal Remount Horse Show and Sale, 27-28 June 1941. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Program - Front Royal-Riverton Bridges Dedication, 1941. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Program - Stonewall Jackson Bust Unveiling, New York University, 1957. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Program - Thanksgiving Dinner, 2nd Battalion, 36th Infantry, Camp Devens, Massachusetts, 1920. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Program - Warren County Centennial, 7-9 August 1936. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Program - Warren County Civil War Centennial Commemoration, Battle of Front Royal, 19-20 May 1962. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Program - "Welcome Home Our Boys," Front Royal, 1919. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Promissory Notes. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Puerto Rico House of Representatives. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Randolph-Macon Academy Catalogs. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Randolph-Macon Woman's College Catalog. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Ration Books. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Report Cards. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Resumes and Letters of Recommendation. (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Roster of Warren County Veterans, C.S.A., 1907. (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Sale of Lots and Maintenance of House. (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - School Notebook - "Nature Study Animals". (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Sears, Roebuck and Company - Orders. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Slave Hire Receipt, 1861. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Southern Teachers' Agency and State Co-Operative Teachers Agency. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Speech - Sen. Strom Thurmond at Dedication of Confederate Museum, Front Royal, 28 June 1959. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Staunton Hill Club Catalog. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Student Orders and Regulations - 99th C.T.D. Aircrew, State Teachers College, Springfield, Missouri, 1944. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Suit Papers. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Survey - "Updike Farm," Rappahannock County, 1924. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1871-1930. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1931-1935. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1936-1939. (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1940-1979. (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Temperance. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Tobacco Sales. (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Victor Records Catalog, 1922. (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Warren County Courthouse - History. (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Will of Mary E. Ferguson. (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Will of Katie J. Owen. (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Series III. Account Books and Ledgers., Extent: 1 box. (Box 11)
  The account books and ledgers are the earliest items in the collection, and date back to 1843. Some of them were kept by Absalom Jordan while he was sheriff of Rappahannock County in the 1850's, and include lists of tax and fee bills due, militia fines, and personal accounts and expenses. There are bank books, memorandum books, a 1918 class roll, a scrapbook containing newspaper clippings, estate accounts of Absalom Jordan, and personal accounts of Mary Katherine Jordan. Also included in this series is a "Character Book" kept by Virginia L. Jordan, 1917-1921, that contains personal facts regarding friends, many of whom were classmates of hers at Front Royal High School.
  - Account Books and Ledgers. (Box 11)
- Series IV. Ephemera., Extent: 1 box. (Box 12)
  The ephemera includes patches and a medal, Confederate States and United States flags, cigarette packages and hand-rolled cigarettes, fabric swatches, souvenir fans, and a deck of cards featuring noted Confederate leaders.
  - Ephemera. (Box 12)
- Series V. Oversize., Extent: 1 folder.
  The oversize items include a house floor plan of 315 Blue Ridge Avenue in Front Royal, the marriage certificate of Katherine Byrd Jordan and Otis O. Owen (1919), United Daughters of the Confederacy membership certificate (1952), chalk drawings of William A. Jordan, Sr. and John Green Newman, and other items.
  - Oversize. (Box PP Oversize Box 64)